<?xml version='1.0' encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="faq">

    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <sect1 id="faq_license">

        <title>What license is the Yellow Duck Framework published under?</title>

        <para>The Yellow Duck Framework is published under the GNU Lesser General Public License. A copy of this license can be found in <xref linkend="appendixD" />.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="faq_learning">

        <title>How do I start learning the Yellow Duck Framework?</title>

        <para>To learn the Yellow Duck Framework, there are different approaches. The following chapters in the userguide will definitely help you to get up and running faster:</para>

        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><xref linkend="firstsample"/></listitem>
            <listitem><xref linkend="tutorial"/></listitem>
            <listitem><xref linkend="ydrequest"/></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Once you read these chapters, you can go through the other chapters to find out more about specific parts of the documentation.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="faq_author">

        <title>Who wrote the Yellow Duck Framework?</title>

        <para>Pieter Claerhout (<ulink url="http://www.yellowduck.be/">www.yellowduck.be</ulink>) wrote the initial Yellow Duck Framework and is still maintaining it.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="faq_support">

        <title>Where can I get support for the Yellow Duck Framework?</title>

        <para>Currently, the only way to get support is to use the online support forum. This forum can be found on the following location: <ulink  url="http://www.yellowduck.be/ydf/forum/" />.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="faq_mailing_list">

        <title>Is there a mailing list?</title>

        <para>No, there is no mailing list and there are no plans to create one.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="faq_contributing">

        <title>How can I contribute?</title>

        <para>If you want to contribute code, you can request write access to the Subversion server by sending an email to <ulink url="mailto:pieter@yellowduck.be">pieter@yellowduck.be</ulink>. However, there are some rules you need to keep in mind when you are contributing code to this project:</para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>All you classes should contain <ulink url="http://www.doxygen.org/">DoxyGen</ulink> docstrings so that they are automatically included in the API documentation.</listitem>
                <listitem>All class names should start with the characters "YD".</listitem>
                <listitem>All constants should start with the characters "YD_".</listitem>
                <listitem>Provide an example (preferable a lot of examples) on how to use the class.</listitem>
                <listitem>Provide documentation about the class you wrote so that this can be included in the standard documentation.</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

    </sect1>

</chapter>
